French researchers are reporting that
they revived human brain tissue
postmortem and used it to run a robot
and it was capable of forming new
memories and acting upon them. And yes,
this is very fascinating and makes me
deeply uncomfortable. We've seen some
major advancements when it comes to
reviving postmortem tissue and there's a
number of reasons why you would want to
do this. In the case of a brain, this is
really a research platform. So you have
something that you can experiment on
that is not an actual person. This came
from organ transplants because yes, you
have to keep organs alive for a little
while and yeah, things like nerves have
also been transplanted. I do need to say
that when it comes to Bext Org, they may
have revived chemical activity but the
brain is not functional. It's not
learning anything but that's not
entirely true about our next study. Now
this was just announced that it's a
preprint and it came from a
well-respected robotics institute in
France, LIRMM. And yes, I checked
because I too was in disbelief. Before
we move forward, I do want to remind
people that these are subsections of
cortex. They are not whole brains.
Although it does certainly seem that
whole brains could be used with combined
research with brain in a vat, i.e. Bext
Org. I know this all sounds very sci-fi
and I'm aware of that which is why I
include citations in the description of
every video. They took subsections of
human cortex just hours after somebody
had expired and then oxygenated it to
keep cellular activity. Then they used
the same mechanisms that we used to hook
up brain organoids or lab-grown brains
to a robot. They have a bidirectional
flow in which electricity can stimulate
nerves and then the nerves can
communicate back with the robot. Even
though the person who used to contain
said brain is no longer alive, they were
able to elicit electrical activity and
it also demonstrated sensory motor
learning. So they used it to control
that electrical hand. Every time it gave
the correct impulse, it would then
control the hand and that hand would
play a note on the piano. They started
with a process called motor babbling in
which it did something very similar to
how babies learn where they just got
random impulses and those impulses could
be associated with a note. Then they
taught it how to play certain notes. So
once it got the correct one, it would
get electrical stimulation reinforcing
that neural pathway. In this way, the
robotic hand learned to play certain
notes in certain orders on the piano and
it had feedback so that the brain could
know what it was actually playing. And
then they wanted to see if it could
learn something new.
So they had a human actually play notes
on a piano. It would be fed into the
microphone and then back to the robot
brain complex. Yeah, the brain was able
to learn a brand new song even though it
is not in a body, even though it is
listening through an interface that
we're not familiar with and even though
it is controlling a robot arm. Yeah, it
was able to learn. This shows that even
postmortem the brain is active. It can
still learn new things. That means that
the end of at least our biological life
is not the end of what our brain is
capable of and that is important
information. You may ask and perhaps
correctly so, why? Why are we doing
this? Well, it may be very useful. We
assume that at the point that somebody
expires their brain rapidly loses the
capacity to function. In fact, when
people are comatose, we decide at what
point the brain is no longer viable.
However, we have demonstrated that the
individual components of the brain at
least are still capable of working and
even learning new things even hours
after somebody is gone. We may have
missed the capacity to help a patient.
We may have underestimated the degree to
which our brain is capable of surviving
and even thriving.
These platforms could be very valuable
when it comes to medical research and
brain in a vat is pretty extreme. So if
we take an entire brain and revive it,
that requires a whole heck of a lot of
specialized equipment and they haven't
been able to keep it alive for very
long. If we just take a little
subsection of cortex and can use that as
a medical research platform, that is
much more efficient and much more
reasonable.
And while organoids are extremely easy
to grow, yes, you can take stem cells
from an adult person. You can even take
skin cells, turn those into stem cells
and then grow that into a brain. It is
essentially a fetal brain.
All of our research on brain organoids
are extremely limited because they show
the effects on a developing person. And
yeah, that is valuable in its own right,
but it doesn't really help for
treatments for adults. And yes, I
suppose that one of the messages and it
was one of the very first things I
thought about, is that it shows that
disembodied human brains postmortem can
run and operate robots. And we're not
talking about fetal brains that have
never experienced the world before.
We're talking about something that has
already had a full life. And no, it's
not conscious. It's a little subsection
of cortex. It's a functional subunit of
a human brain. It's not the brain
itself. Although we really don't know
that much about it. We don't know how
experiences would change their ability
to learn. This would also allow us to
study neurodegenerative conditions and
try out treatments, too.
Would I want to be placed in a robot
postmortem? Yes, I think that would be
fun. Would I just want to be a brain in
a vat? No.
Did this paper make me stare at the roof
for a good hour contemplating the
meaning of life and suffering? Yes. Yes,
it did. I do hope you've enjoyed this. I
will keep you up-to-date on the cutting
edge. Follow for more.